[SPEAKER_02]: So, I had a question about upadāna, often translated as assumption.
[SPEAKER_02]: The
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole idea behind the kind of translation of assumption is that it is something that you're not really even aware of.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, somebody who doesn't know they're adopted just assumes that they're not adopted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not even on their radar as a view they hold until they're confronted with something that indicates otherwise.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how could you possibly get to the point where you are beyond assumptions, which is
[SPEAKER_02]: The state of the arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you know that there's nothing that you're assuming anymore?
[SPEAKER_02]: It seems like an impossible state.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it would seem impossible if... that's actually a common thing, that the truth is thought of as a... some sort of external... on some sort of external level, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Practicing the dhamma to find out the truth, meaning some sort of metaphysical principle that underlies the universe or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on that level, yes, you will never be sure that you understood everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, technically, the dhamma is not really...
[SPEAKER_00]: At least not in the sense that people think of reality, like finding out the truth of reality, because, yeah, that notion of reality is really not
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha was talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's some external assumption, two or five aggregates of some kind of a external principle that underlies other people and that you can be aware of independently of your point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would know that you're free from assumption, first of all, by understanding the level where assumptions are, which is in regard to your own relationship with
[SPEAKER_00]: Any ideas about the truth of reality, for example, like, assumptions would happen in regard to you thinking about this.
[SPEAKER_00]: While you're thinking about what the truth of reality is, philosophizing about that stuff, there would be assumptions there, on that internal level that matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is the most fundamental assumption?
[SPEAKER_00]: That this is to talk about, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like assumption, assumption in general.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha said there are four types of assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not apart from that, so...
[SPEAKER_02]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, like, to kind of use that example again of the adopted.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like when you become an arahant, you, like, find out you're actually adopted.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, it's not on that level of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, to answer your question, self-view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, assumption, self-view meaning you assume that things belong to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's that's the fundamental assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even when you contemplate, and not everything, by the way, it's not like Truth of Anatta is about finding out that
[SPEAKER_00]: Things out there, like every mountain I see, every wall I see, every, I don't know, block of wood I see, I need to remind myself that it's anatta.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are things that are... that you already recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the assumption is, specifically, in regard to those more personal things in your own experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are those personal things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well,
[SPEAKER_00]: Form, feeling, perception, intention, and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the assumption is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will know that you're free from assumption, first of all, by... Well, by knowing what is... First of all, you find out what assumption is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the first... the first, eh... like, eh... milestone that you need to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is that assumption of self?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it just holding a belief, like consciously, that things are mine?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, perhaps we should clear up whether there's a distinction between, let's say, belief, opinions and assumptions, because assumptions is basically on the level of view, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, we're not just talking about opinions and beliefs, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that you can easily change.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, almost every dedicated Buddhist already has the belief that there is no self.
[SPEAKER_03]: The belief of anath, essentially.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That then becomes another problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And yet, they're not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how can that... That's clearly, then, as you said, it's not on the same level.
[SPEAKER_03]: Assumption and belief is not on the same level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that is generally the case.
[SPEAKER_04]: And now, in particular, we should clear up that the Buddha actually never really taught
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, almost to make a physical statement, there is no self.
[SPEAKER_04]: His teaching is about recognizing how things are not self.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is not just like, oh, whether you add a T to the no or not, that is just splitting hairs.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is a very fundamental difference, because to start out by saying there is no self, is in a sense already the now of the problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whereas,
[SPEAKER_04]: Once it's clear that the whole problem is to realize that things are not self, then it is about how you are regarding things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's when people would think it's about the belief of self, like this metaphysical, almost, concept.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you define the self?
[SPEAKER_03]: People would think it's about that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, like you said, the Buddha never discussed it in those terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's actually, you have a sense of self, because you take things as yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not like, first you start with the sense of self, that you have to define in such and such a way, and then, because that self exists, then that self takes things up.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why, whenever the Buddha would talk about not-self, he would emphasize form is not-self, feeling is not-self, perception is not-self, intention is not-self, consciousness is not-self.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: Anything that you would take as self would have to be one of those five things.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, by seeing that nothing can be self on that level, you don't need to care one bit about defining what the self is.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will know that because you no longer take
[SPEAKER_03]: The entirety of experience is mine, which is the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, there is no sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's the assumption.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's really what the assumption is.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not like I have a wrong belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if I ask you, what is the self?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you gave me a wrong answer or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not what the wrong view means.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means taking, on any level,
[SPEAKER_00]: Any aspect of your experience is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you assume, like, if you have a...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, something that... Actually, the Buddha gave a simile, like a... like a borrowed jewelry, and you may not even know that it's borrowed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you assume that it's yours, and you act with it as if
[SPEAKER_00]: It's yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, suddenly, you know, I don't know, let's say you went to a party or something, and you're wearing all the jewelry, and getting a lot of pleasure out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, suddenly, you see the person who is the actual owner of the jewelry, and he takes it away right at that moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you... that's, practically speaking, you're assuming that that jewelry is yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the same with the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything can go well for quite a while, but the fact that the state of affairs is contrary to how you assume it to be, in this case that it does belong to you, eventually it will become clear that it's not actually the case, because...
[SPEAKER_00]: At some point, something you don't want will be experienced, something you want will fade away, and that's how your assumption is proved wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would you know that there is no assumption?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, not by thinking of it in those abstract terms, like, could I get the idea about what not-self is wrong, but by asking yourself
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there any possibility that if things change in any way, in any direction, that I'm... even that I might not expect, or it hasn't happened before, that I would suffer?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a measure of whether there is assumption or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether there is something that could make you suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not even like... it's not like you can deceive yourself about this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you have a basic sense of authenticity, as we discussed before, you need very little reflection, actually, to see that there is still suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, that's your measure of the assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like how right your beliefs are on a conceptual level, but how possible is it that suffering might arise for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the size of your assumption
[SPEAKER_00]: is the size of how much suffering there could be and how many things could cause it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on account of reducing the size of that assumption, the size of the suffering would also decrease.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like the noble disciples.
[SPEAKER_00]: They still have some degree of assumption, but it can never be
[SPEAKER_00]: Nearly the same amount as a pūtugina.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, as the Buddha said, it's like seven grains of sand for a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the size of the assumption compared to the size of the pūtugina's assumption, the assumption itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, seven grains of sand compared to the whole Himalayas.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's the...
[SPEAKER_03]: If there is suffering, there has...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, if there is assumption, there has to be suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there is suffering, there has to be assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's really your measure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, if you have developed that criteria of authenticity that we discussed before, then you know for sure how to investigate your liability.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know how to see whether you're liable to something or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, that's how asking yourself
[SPEAKER_00]: Death, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sickness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Aging.
[SPEAKER_00]: People usually think of the practice as some sort of... these mystical truths that you discover that are very pleasant to find out how your consciousness is constantly changing every second or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the dhamma starts with the Buddha himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: He went forth
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he wanted to find a way out of sickness, aging and death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because he wanted to find out these very...
[SPEAKER_04]: The ultimate tools of the universe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is... that is the... everything that he taught.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assumption, ignorance, all of that pertains to that liability to sickness, aging and death.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any person who, even a sotāpanna or anāgāmī even,
[SPEAKER_00]: If they reflect properly, they would be able to see, just by thinking, by reflecting, oh, are there things that could cause suffering in this mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: And the answer will have to be yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's really about, like, developing that self-transparency, so that your questioning of your liability to suffering is accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And based on that, you indirectly know, okay, there is assumption left.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, ordinary to you would be, I exist and then, because I exist, I have desire for this and I regard things like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you just said that actually assumption of self is secondary.
[SPEAKER_04]: It is the product of taking things as mine.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, in order to uproot that assumption, can we explore in more detail
[SPEAKER_04]: What is involved in regarding things as mine?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because when that becomes more clear, the result will be that there is no longer room for assumption of self.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what is then practically involved in regarding things as mine?
[SPEAKER_04]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: Attending rightly things, so not recognizing or discerning the womb of things, or attending without yonisona and sikkhāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in this way, you basically take the experience, beginning of the experience, from the point of self, yeah?
[SPEAKER_02]: First is, I am the first one, and I'm attending to anything out there,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that would be the wrong type of attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there something more concrete, even before that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, in terms of... you mean like precepts?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'd have to basically prepare the ground for it, so to speak, by keeping the...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, is it by acting out of pressure that one is practically regarding things as mine?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, can you act out of pressure without you already regarding things as mine?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, does every acting out of pressure necessarily implies that you take things to be yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's even like pressure, and you can sort of particularize it into passion, aversion, and destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: The acting out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know that if you have such actions,
[SPEAKER_01]: With no regard whatsoever for your abstract ideas about not-self, you have a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, by committing those actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, that's an important thing I forgot to bring up.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha said, in one sutta, he talked about 11 things that, if you don't understand, it's impossible for you to make progress in the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Madhyaminikaya 33 or 34, he said, one of them was, a bhikkhu does not understand, a fool is determined by his actions, and the wise person is determined by their actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because, it sounds like, okay, sure, but if you think about it, many people would actually overlook that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would think, you can have wisdom,
[SPEAKER_01]: By, you know, having these abstract sort of very mystical ideas about emptiness and not-self and how consciousness changes and, you know, the mind moments and the train of stream of consciousness or whatever.
[SPEAKER_04]: All of it has already little to do with the dhamma, just to be clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, at the same time, then they continue to act out of passion, aversion, and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, from that point of view, according to the Buddha's definition, that person remains a fool just as much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they are acting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, a fool is determined by his actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: A wise person is determined by his actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person who understands anatta,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be determined by the actions that they do, more importantly than by what... That's really what's revealing your assumptions, like what actions you do, rather than your intellectual... What you say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, that's even also like a way of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Recognizing a good teacher, yes, you have to stay, live with him for a long time.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's also from the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to stay for a long time and see him in different situations.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, when he's being praised or criticized, you know, basically he's being challenged.
[SPEAKER_02]: Only then, on account of basically seeing him in this different, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: Pressing situations, you can judge, okay, now I can see that there is a...
[SPEAKER_02]: I can't see greed there, or aversion.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you can catch some glimpse of that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you see, now you say a fool is determined by his actions and a wise person is determined by his actions, but somebody comes along and says, well, I thought noble disciple who understands not-self, so how can there be any action when there is no longer self?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how can a wise person, someone who understands not-self, how can there still be action defining that individual?
[SPEAKER_04]: Right?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's a very common idea, but it's not accurate.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if we want to go into the truth of the statement that the fool is determined by his actions and a wise person is determined by his actions, if this is not going to give rise to those kind of questions, we should perhaps say something more about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, that would already be coming from the same kind of mystical idea, like not-self means like, oh, there's nobody here, or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, like nobody's acting, everything is just happening, you didn't decide to do anything at all, it's just the spontaneous activity of the universe.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's precisely, or you can say, oh, it's just consciousness arising and passing, or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you read the suttas, and it seems like you're saying the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then it's contradicting the very statement, because then
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha said there are things that the arhant is incapable of doing on account of the freedom from greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't say, oh, arhant, you know, there's no arhant, so this is not really... this is not really happening or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: These actions don't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it says there are things that he is incapable of doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it also says,
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, in another sutta, it says here a person might see or might think, oh, he is restrained out of... because he's restrained because he's not free.
[SPEAKER_01]: He remains in seclusion because he's still not free.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's dedicated to, you know, virtue because he's still not free.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the sutta says no, it should not be seen that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because he's intent on the absence of attachment, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he's speaking about an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's not saying, like, he has no choice to, you know, it's just a process or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's saying that
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's choosing to still be restrained, still keep the virtues, still do these things, on account of a preference for non-attachment, preference for non-trailing in all this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like...
[SPEAKER_01]: With that view, actually, even what we usually call the mundane right view, it would be like you become an arahant by really saying there is no action, there is no fruits of good and bad actions, there is no mother, there is no father.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's essentially what the view of freedom is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, you have to reach freedom while still recognizing and taking on that there is action, there is results.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is you who is doing this, not somebody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not happening by itself or any of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, kind of, by trying to shortcut into what you think the right you is, you actually end up somewhere completely different.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Which is happening a lot in the name of, well, Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, this is why I thought we could spend some time dwelling on these wrong ideas.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the difficulty is then to see how can there be action against the background of the truth of not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because, say, when the Buddha talked about
[SPEAKER_01]: Being free from kamma doesn't mean, again, in this mystical sense of, like, there is action, but really there is no action, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... when he explained why is form impermanent, why is perception impermanent, he said it's because
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were... well, in order for it to be self, you would have to be able to say, may my form be like this, may my form not be like this, may my feeling be like this, may my feeling not be like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was literally the second discourse he gave.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is... it's not that there is no self, again, because of this metaphysical truth that things are not real or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because of the lack of control that you have over things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: You would see absence of action would be through the understanding that even if you do something, that's being done because form, feeling, perception, intention, and consciousness is allowing you to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's kind of like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, in the past, with the self-view, you would have believed that you yourself were the one making, you know, moving things around, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, it's not like there is no movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, every time you want to do something, you actually have to submit a proposal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then your boss is the one who does it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But before, you assume that, no, it's like direct, kind of like, I make a choice and then the result comes about, like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you understand, actually, there's a middleman there, that you were kind of missing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because most of the time, things went
[SPEAKER_01]: As you planned, like you wanted pleasure and you managed to get it, you wanted pain, you managed to avoid it, you forgot that there's actually a middleman there between you wanting something and the result actually coming about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's the aggregates, like it's the the impermanence of... or the uncertainty of these things makes makes it so that
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that you will never get what you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, factually, there are times where you can achieve your wishes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, it always goes through that middleman.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because of that, if you understand that, you'll be able to understand, oh, there is no... like... it's unjustifiable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It actually does me much more harm than good to assume myself to be able to directly exert control over things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is that relative degree of control, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, eh...
[SPEAKER_04]: Because otherwise, there would be no path, no practice, no freedom.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, also, like, the arahant would be like some sort of robot functioning on deterministic principles or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: But... And becoming an arahant would not just become something random that we can choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as well, it would be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Some people actually, even in the Buddha's time, he said, some people misrepresent me by saying that I teach the annihilation of an existing being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, you hear that statement and you might think, oh, so they're explicitly saying, like, oh, you're annihilationist.
[SPEAKER_01]: But really, annihilationism is also included in this very view that by supposedly understanding anatta, like, now it's just a process and it's just... happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Happening, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is annihilationism.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, like, you had a self before and through this practice
[SPEAKER_01]: You made it so that now there's only a process.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you annihilated the existing being that was there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, some people misrepresent me by saying that's my teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what happens even today.
[SPEAKER_01]: People would think it's kind of, I had a self before,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, through this practice, I destroyed it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, the sense of self, it's not on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like I said, it's that assumption of that direct control.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you abandon it, when you abolish it, there is still
[SPEAKER_01]: Individual, as the Buddha said, bhūgala is the word for individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is still a kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's why arahants would have different tendencies, for example, like, you know, Mahākassapa, for example, he wanted to stay in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha asked him to come with him, to live in the more comfortable environment, and he said no.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whenever, you know, various events and stuff
[SPEAKER_01]: Ananda, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, or one of them, Anya Kandanya, the first disciple, he was so, like, disillusioned with this idea of more people.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, he was fond of the seclusion so much, basically, that as soon as he became an arahant, he left and he didn't see the Buddha for, like, 20 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, there were other arahants who were, you know, quite happy to help out the new monks and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it were just, like, some sort of, again, deterministic, like, deletion of
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so this middleman that you were talking about, that is the five aggregates themselves, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So it's like...
[SPEAKER_04]: So everything that you...
[SPEAKER_04]: Assumed five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, okay, so that raises the question, is there still a middleman in the arahant's case?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, like, fully understanding that there is a middleman, is how you would abandon the assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's... Like, the assumption is of the direct... Yeah, of the... yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how... so, how can one
[SPEAKER_04]: Reflect on that wisely.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, everything that you want to do, that is to say, every intention that you think is yours, is possible only because you find yourself in a wider situation that allows you to attend in that way.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, your intentions are never in isolation, like, oh, I want to go and make a tea.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's possible only because there happens to be a kitchen with a kettle and tea and all the rest of it and there's this body.
[SPEAKER_04]: So,
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that intention has to be seen as fully embedded within the totality of this evision experience.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, when that intention is taken as my intention in that direct sense, that entire context is being overlooked.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that intention is being seen in isolation.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that is how it never exists.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just tell somebody whose legs got amputated to start walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, even us, healthy people, we can do stuff because the body allows you to do it first.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you might develop all sorts of notions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, my body and all this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, having views that this is not my body, that doesn't...
[SPEAKER_01]: In and of itself, if you don't see why it's not my body, if you just apply this view, which is what usually happens, that's not making any difference, because it's like you just... in the same way that somebody would believe in God or something, and through that conviction, you just paste it over everything,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, now, it's a similar principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just pasting this ideal, which could have been anything else, really, over things like, this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's no reason for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just accept that view and you're applying it to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you need to understand, why is it that things are not mine?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, recognize it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Realize it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because dhammas aren't here now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's not something you have to, kind of, explain yourself or... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it exists for you as a view, but actually, you find things in this way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why... Yeah, and not... and it would have to be not like... because really, that's the implication.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, before, when I didn't know about this,
[SPEAKER_01]: Things were different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now that I know about this mystical truth of anatta, now things are like that, because it is a kind of a fabricated, derived idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not... it doesn't fit the criteria of the dhamma being directly visible, as the Buddha said, because there was, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Tell a farmer or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to talk to a farmer now, let alone in, you know, ancient India, about how his mind is composed of 52 different types of mind moments, and every single one is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then try to tell him, you know, give an explanation of that and see if he would actually tell you, oh, yeah, this is directly visible.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: In fact, that's just another mystical assumption.
[SPEAKER_04]: This whole idea that things change or flicker in and out of existence very quickly, more quickly than you can manage to keep track of with your mindfulness,
[SPEAKER_04]: Or with your awareness or something.
[SPEAKER_04]: Therefore, it only appears as if things endure.
[SPEAKER_04]: But behind the scene, i.e.
[SPEAKER_04]: that's the difference between appearance and the ultimate reality then, they really flicker in and out of existence.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then the whole practice of meditation becomes to gain a certain speed of your mindfulness in order to observe the gaps of things flickering in and out of existence.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's full-blown mystical view.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And see, that's not directly visible.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, that's not right.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, but you see, but then people will say, no, no, I need to have very deep meditation, so that that mystical tooth becomes directly visible to me.
[SPEAKER_03]: But see, that didn't... so that didn't exist.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you brought this thing about.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That was not there before.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't include you, because you are still that kind of, you know, observer.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your point of view from outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Looking at it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, that's...
[SPEAKER_03]: I wanted to get into that as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: So,
[SPEAKER_03]: The view of impermanence, of suffering in oneself...
[SPEAKER_03]: If impermanence is taken as this, like you said, things flickering in and out of existence, then it's easy to explain, oh, so anatta means, like, there is no self, because if everything is constantly changing, there is no identity of things, like, nothing remains the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: But again, you don't find a single sutta where the Buddha explained not-self in those terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: He always used the analogy or the metaphor of trying to control something, like,
[SPEAKER_03]: He gave the simile of, if you would find random sticks and branches in the forest, and then somebody would come and burn them, and then would you be, like, affected and thinking, oh, why are you burning us?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why are you burning me?
[SPEAKER_03]: On account of, like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Even if you could see them flickering in and out of existence?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, even if you could have that vision,
[SPEAKER_03]: You're still going to take that flickering in and out of existence as... Like, there is an exertion of assumption of control there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you haven't understood the sense of self for what it is, then you might very well be having, you know... Well, most of the time, it would be like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you were...
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a exertion of that assumed intention without that middleman, as I just mentioned, towards you getting that vision of things constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't see, for example, that even that experience of
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing things constantly changing depends on having a healthy body, having a healthy mind, having, you know, not being dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see that middleman.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the assumption of self is very much still there, because you think you have... Like, I mean, just imagine, you've got this vision of the constant flux of things, and everything makes sense, and you're enlightened now, and then tomorrow you don't have it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just happen to forget.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so then, if you suffered on account of that, means that was not a not-self, that you're not seeing that self, because it had to lead to freedom from any sort of appropriation.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and then, you're gonna exert yourself in order to get that experience again.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so there, that right there, is the assumption of control.
[SPEAKER_03]: I want, may my perception be thus,
[SPEAKER_03]: May my consciousness be thus.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is the assumption of self, right there.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's entirely missing the point.
[SPEAKER_04]: And even if there would be stuff flickering in and out of existence, in order to even... that can... that itself can never be outside the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you see, it is those...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that is just not... it doesn't add up, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, so, um...
[SPEAKER_03]: What I wanted to get to, as well, is that these three characteristics... Oh, before I get into that, actually...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you wouldn't see from this sequence, like, things constantly changing, therefore, they have no lasting identity.
[SPEAKER_03]: But where's the dukkha part?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there is no inherent suffering in the fact that you have perpetual novelty.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, the Buddha said, suffering is because of anicca.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how is it that suffering would be a natural conclusion of this flux?
[SPEAKER_03]: It just doesn't follow.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, in order for you to suffer on account of the impermanence of things, there needs to have been
[SPEAKER_03]: Some sort of lasting of the thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Otherwise, like, how can you talk about the thing that I'm attached to, which might change?
[SPEAKER_04]: So... Yeah, so you never would have become attached to something if it wasn't on account of regarding that thing as permanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but if that thing didn't endure for more than a mind moment, how could you have developed the attachment in the first place?
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, there comes all this sort of patchwork, just saying like, well, yeah, the attachment, you have multiple mind moments of attachment following one after the other, but that's like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, then you can just further down that same rabbit hole.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it's just... yeah, that's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so... so... the... the point is, as I've kept repeating, the dhamma is directly visible.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, everyone... the aniccas, dukkha and anatta that the Buddha is talking about, is something that the Buddha... that everyone already sees, because it's... he doesn't say the noble one
[SPEAKER_03]: He just understands anatta.
[SPEAKER_03]: It says noble ones understands all saṅkharas are anicca, all saṅkharas are dukkha, all dhammas are not-self.
[SPEAKER_03]: But this not everybody sees.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, but everybody sees.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everybody can see this is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is not mine.
[SPEAKER_03]: You mean some object in the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, something, some specific thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what they cannot see is
[SPEAKER_03]: There's the other one as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything that is of the nature of arising is of the nature of ceasing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the understanding that actually takes you... Well, that's what qualifies as enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, anicca is not like you... To see the anicca itself, there is nothing like, you know, rocket science about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's... You see a tree, and you know that it's liable to die at some point.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the problem is,
[SPEAKER_03]: There are things in your own experience that you don't see having that same nature as that tree.
[SPEAKER_03]: Meaning, your form, your body, your feelings, your perceptions, your intentions, your consciousness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, even if you give everything up, like you live under a bridge or something, and you never eat, and you don't do anything,
[SPEAKER_03]: When your perceptions change, you will still be affected, as if this thing was supposed to last forever.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's what... you can't see the entirety of your experience as impermanent, as suffering, as not-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the concept of impermanence, suffering, not-self, is really nothing like...
[SPEAKER_04]: But another disciple can see the entirety of experience as
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what I'm saying is, that is the work.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is what the Putugin is lacking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Being able to see the entirety of the experience in that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, he already knows what anicca, dukkha, anatta is in a mundane sense, but he doesn't see it in regard to form, feeling, perception.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, he doesn't even see the aggregates to begin with.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that really is the work.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, how do I recognize the aggregates?
[SPEAKER_03]: And then,
[SPEAKER_03]: These three characteristics will become apparent immediately.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So first, one needs to apprehend what these aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right?
[SPEAKER_04]: As you just mentioned.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because otherwise, how is it possible to start regarding them as anicca, dukkha, and anatta?
[SPEAKER_04]: If that phenomena has not been designated correctly, then even if you do it sort of rightly, it will still be too limited in order to bring about the
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the insight of entering the path, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so it's not like... Usually, again, the tendency would be, okay, I'm meditating, I'm making all this effort, so I get to understand what anicca really is.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, it's... What you need to do is uncover, like, what your experience is in the first place, so that it becomes apparent that this is anicca.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what the signs of the mind, that the suttas talk about, that would be revealed only on account of seclusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, well, in seclusion, you get to see... Actually, the Buddha said that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Based... a bhikkhu who is secluded...
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, there's seclusion by body and mind, but in this sutta, he just used the word secluded, and he said, a bhikkhu who is secluded, what does he see?
[SPEAKER_03]: He sees such as the arising of form, such as the cessation of form, such as the arising of feeling, such as the cessation of feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: But again, if you think it's this very complex mind moments of these things constantly changing, no, it's you're sitting there, having thoughts about this, about that, and
[SPEAKER_03]: That, right there, is already the arrogance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not like you need to take this microscope and start looking harder.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right now, as we're talking, form is arising, form is ceasing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's on the level, really, of more general, rather than focusing harder on particular moments.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's... you will get to see, okay, how do I see feeling?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is feeling?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do I feel now?
[SPEAKER_03]: Pleasant, unpleasant, neutral.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, this feeling now, I have various attitudes towards it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I want to get more of it if it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, did I not have a different feeling yesterday?
[SPEAKER_03]: And I was also trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I was also trying to get more of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, oh, so that's what feeling is.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not something mystical.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's right there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then,
[SPEAKER_03]: If it's clearly happening that... Like, I always want my feelings to remain pleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: I never want them to...
[SPEAKER_03]: If feelings were obeying my will, an unpleasant feeling would never have arisen in the first place.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, see, that's already closer to a reflection of... on anicca, dukkha, anatta.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, for as long as the person hasn't got the right view, well, it's because
[SPEAKER_03]: Not because of the anicca part, but because, well, okay, you saw some extent of feeling, but there's always more layers of it to be revealed, for example.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's really what you would have to emphasize, like, how to recognize my experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not particular mind moments, but this experience now, sitting here.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where you would find these these characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and that's how, like, without having to...
[SPEAKER_03]: If you didn't have special meditation sessions or something every day to practice this, you would be able to remain with the perspective of anicca, dukkha, anatta, even though when you're going around doing work or something that that takes all of your attention, you don't have time to be watching the moments flickering in and out, but you do know that that same experience as a whole
[SPEAKER_03]: That was there when you were alone, reflecting, like I mentioned.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that same experience as a whole is there now.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, but if it were about this, watching these, you know, esoteric phenomena, well, that's not going to be there anymore when you come out of your... when you open your eyes, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not going to be there anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that applied to a very limited scope.